WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
- Synced and corrected by VitoSilans -
-- www.MY-SUBS.com --
And at the first blush of the oak leaves,
we head to the Grove.
The only trouble is there's a
hundred perils between here and there.
I'm peril.
Stop!
Our light is fading.
And this mithril... It is our only salvation?
So the fate of the entire Elven race...
- ...is in your hands.
- Hmm.
Nampat!
Sauron was once your people's
enemy as much as mine.
I call on you to reforge the alliance
between Númenor and Elves.
To save the men of the Southlands.
Give it to me.
It's under here.
All hail to the true
King of the Southlands.
All hail!
Take shelter!
The Queen!
Theo!
Help!
Halbrand!
Elendil!
Mother? Mother?
Mother!
Over here.
Come here.
- Are you hurt?
- No.
Stay with me.
Come on.
Where's Ontamo? Ontamo was with me.
Crawl.
Crawl. I won't leave you.
Soldier, over here!
Valandil.
Soldier, he's gone.
He's gone.
This way!
- He's gone...
- Come on!
- Help! Please, help!
- Soldiers!
Over here! We're inside!
That roof's about to come down.
- Can't get out!
- Quickly, clear a path.
Over here. This way.
Take hold of my hand. You're all right.
Go forward. Stay together.
- Hurry, my Queen.
- Go.
Go towards the bridge.
Get them out of here!
No!
Isildur!
♪ Old Bolgerbuck went snailing ♪
♪ One autumn day so fine ♪
♪ He found a hundred big ones ♪
♪ I wish that they were mine ♪
Up ahead.
The Grove! I think this is it.
Said that three days ago.
No, no, he's right. I remember this.
Come on.
Do you smell that? Wood smoke!
The others must've started bakin'.
Mr. Burrows.
What happened?
My great-grand used
to speak of mountains
to the south that could spit fire-rock.
He said they go to sleep.
Sometimes for hundreds of years.
Only to wake again when
a new evil is rising.
- Hmm.
- Brandyfoot.
Your friend up there. The big fella.
- You don't suppose...
- Suppose what?
Maybe he could fix it.
- Go on, Nori.
- Yes. Like he fixed those wolves.
- Uh, I don't know... I don't know if he...
- What you waitin' for?
He's done so much for us.
It's a mite rude of
us to ask more of him.
I see.
I'll ask him, then.
Sadoc!
Out the way, little ones.
Á keuta...
Á envinyata...
Envinyata...
Lótë na...
- Lótë na...
- What's he mutterin'?
Likely little words, so
the tree'll understand.
Sadoc, trees don't talk.
Some do.
Don't distract him.
Envinyata!
Lótë na!
Great-goats. It's working...
Á kuita! Á kuita! Á kuita!
He's fixin' it.
Just like Sadoc said he would.
Á kuita!
Dilly, get back!
- No!
- Nori!
My sweet girls! My babies!
Nori! Dilly! Dilly.
Dilly, Nori, are you all right?
There you go.
Are you all right? Are you all right?
I'm all right. I said.
I'm all...
We ask for something
sacred from this mountain.
And so we offer something
sacred in return.
In exchange for access
to your mithril mines,
the Elves are prepared
to furnish this city
with game, grain,
and timber from the
elder forests of Eriador
for the next five centuries.
Five centuries?
Quite a promise, if they can keep it...
I never made a promise I didn't.
I see you've learned a
few words of stone-tongue.
Impressive.
Tell me, why should we trust any Elf?
You should not.
But you can trust me.
For I am no common Elf,
but Elrond Half-elven.
And I see in Elves that which
they cannot see in themselves.
That is why I stand
before you now, alone...
Pleading.
For you to save my people.
Please, noble King. Help us.
I will speak to my son now.
What is to be your answer, Father?
It is said that when
Aulë created our people,
he crafted us of two elements.
Fire and rock.
The rock that lives within
us hungers for the eternal,
resisting the pull of time.
But the fire embraces truth.
That all things must
one day be consumed...
- ...and fade away to ash...
- Father...
We do not dig in earth
that cannot support it.
Delving into depths beyond the darkness.
Tempting shadow, rock, and mine to
bury us all beneath the mountain.
I will not risk Dwarven lives
to help the Elves cheat death.
Cheat death?
Father!
My friend is drowning,
reaching for me to pull him to shore.
You expect me to swat his hand away
because you're afraid
of a bloody rock fall?
The fate of the Elves
was decided many Ages ago.
By minds much wiser,
much farther-seeing than our own.
Defy their will, and this
entire kingdom might fall.
Perhaps the entire Middle-earth.
I am sorry, my son.
But their time has come.
Lice-bearded, uncaring, old fool!
What if he's right?
You're not thinking
of lettin' this happen!
What choice do we have?
You said the other Dwarf-lords
were open to the proposal.
If we reopen the mine ourselves,
prove to them there's a
safe way to gather mithril,
perhaps they'd make him listen.
Perhaps we could force
your father's hand.
He's more than just my father, Disa.
He's our king.
What kind of father would I be
if I teach our children
the will of a king
should be counted as dross
to be cast to the wind?
All right, fine.
I shouldn't have said
he had lice in his beard.
- Or called him a fool.
- Yeah.
No.
No, I detest it when you
heap slag on my mother.
Uh, well, in your mother's case,
she actually does have lice in her...
I'm joking. I'm joking.
Don't suppose I can elbow
you into staying for dinner?
Gil-galad must be informed.
And soon, he will no longer be a king,
for there will no longer be a Lindon.
So this is goodbye, then?
We do not say goodbye.
- We say namá...
- Namárië.
It means more than simply "farewell."
It means... "Go towards goodness."
Elrond!
Why'd they do this?
To make this their home.
Their Shadow Land.
So we take it back, and drive them off.
We have neither position, nor reinforcement.
These lands are dead.
We must rally to the living.
Or put steel down their throats!
It is over.
Not for me. I won't allow it!
We must!
We must.
What are you so bothered
about? It isn't your fault.
Yes, it is.
Keep moving. That's it.
Help those people at the back there.
Isildur?
- The Queen!
- She's alive.
- Is she hurt?
- Save us!
- Is she all right?
Thank goodness!
My Queen.
Take my horse.
Captain, you...
- Captain...
- Where is he?
Where is my son?
They're dead, aren't they?
Arondir. My friends. My...
My mother. Everyone.
What cannot be known hollows the
mind. Fill it not with guesswork.
Where are we even going?
Númenor set their camp upon that ridgeline,
beyond that far peak.
That is where they shall hie
to, along with any survivors.
Your mother included.
And be wary. The Orcs
will move in daylight now.
I've killed Orcs before, you know.
When I was your age, there
was no such thing as Orcs.
And now? How many have you killed?
- Many.
- Good.
I would not use such words.
Why not?
It darkens the heart, to
call dark deeds "good."
It gives place for evil
to thrive inside us.
Every war is fought
both without and within.
Of that, every soldier must be mindful.
Even I. Even you.
Am I a soldier, then?
Perhaps we can make one of you yet.
How much further until
we reach the encampment?
It's just beyond this rise.
How much further until
we're clear of this smoke?
Hold here.
How long have we been clear of it?
Nearly a mile.
I see.
Do you?
Only gray.
Keep walking, both of you.
Guide my horse. No one need notice.
Elendil?
Elendil, please.
Keep walking.
They call it Greenwood the Great.
Keep your head down and your
eye on that line of cliffs.
You'll find the big folk
settlements on the far side.
With any luck, the people there
can help you find your stars.
'Cause all I can tell you is,
Harfoot-folk haven't seen 'em
since the days our ancestors
lived in parts unknown
over a thousand years ago.
And that's a long time to wander.
Even for a fellow with big legs.
Should've just stayed on-trail.
When I saw that star falling,
I should've just let it alone.
- Elanor...
- You tried to tell me, Mother.
But now I understand.
I'm just a Harfoot.
That's all I'll ever be.
Off to bed, Nori.
We can tend to the rest in the mornin'.
Have you ever lost someone close?
To them?
Kin, I mean.
My brother. Finrod.
And my husband.
Husband?
Celeborn was his name.
We met in a glade of flowers.
I was dancing and he saw me there.
You were dancing?
The war seemed so very far away then.
When he went to it, I chided him.
His armor didn't fit properly.
I called him a silver clam.
I never saw him again after that.
My lady.
What you said before...
You're wrong.
It isn't your fault.
It's mine.
You did not intend for this to happen.
I gave power to the enemy.
So that makes me responsible.
Some say that is the way of things.
But I believe the wise also
look upon what is in our hearts.
And this was not in yours.
Do not take the burden of this
day upon your shoulders, Theo.
You may find it difficult
to put it down again.
But how am I to let it go?
There are powers beyond
darkness at work in this world.
Perhaps on days such as this,
we've little choice but
to trust to their designs.
And surrender our own.
My home is gone.
Where's the design in that?
I cannot yet see it.
Stop.
Shut it.
What is it? What do you smell?
Huh?
Ashes.
Nothin' but ashes.
Come on. We're wasting time.
Rest while you can.
We move at first light.
What light?
Another tremor.
We need to give the
rocks time to resettle.
No.
Self-discipline, master Elf.
Think that'll bring you success?
It did in our contest.
Did it?
No.
You lost on purpose?
My aim was never to defeat you,
but to gain your ear a while longer.
Elf lies.
I was...
Winded.
Blast it.
I always thought you were
a mite Dwarvish for an Elf.
And you are a rather
Elvish Dwarf, Durin.
Son of Durin.
- Grandson of...
- Scoff if you like.
The mightiest thing a Dwarf can do is
to be worthy of the name of his father.
We do have our secret names,
for use only amongst ourselves.
And we reveal them only to family.
Wives, parents, sisters, brothers.
- Elrond...
- Save it, Durin.
For the far side.
Aye.
Durin...
Father...
It's more than we ever imagined.
- King Durin, there is a...
- Enough!
Father, just look at it.
Seize the Elf.
When your mother bore you,
something inside you was ill-formed.
Your breathing was ragged and dry.
A tiny, pitiful sound,
like scraping chalkstones.
Folk said you'd never
see your first winter.
And every night,
after your mother's weeping
eyes had found refuge in sleep,
I held you to the firelight,
kept your chin up all night long.
Seemed to ease the burden a little.
And one night,
I gazed down on your tiny, naked face,
and I saw upon it
the great gray beard
of an old Dwarven-king.
Mighty and terrible as
an army with banners.
And when your mother woke, I told her,
she need cry no more.
Our son would live and
he would move mountains!
How do you expect me to
move mountains, Father,
if you fall to pieces
when I dig a single hole?
You speak of greatness for me,
but you suffocate in me any ambition,
any desire,
any thought that does
not originate in you.
The iron that must bear
the most heavy of burdens
must also endure the
most rigorous tempering!
Consigning your allies
to death is not tempering.
Elrond is as much a brother to me
as if he'd been fired
in my own mother's womb.
How dare you...
How dare you!
Invoke your mother's memory
to defend your decision
to betray your own kind?
No! It's you that's betrayed our kind!
Squandering our future so
you can cling to the past!
You profane the crown you wear!
Leave it.
It's not yours anymore.
♪ And while he was a snailin' ♪
♪ Upon that autumn day ♪
♪ His babe he left a-wailin' ♪
♪ The stream took her away ♪
- Poppy?
- Hmm?
What are you doin'?
Fetchin' a pail, what's it look like?
No, the vittles. Stop
eatin'! We have to save those.
Why don't you take a look
outside, and then we'll talk.
What...
Look at that! Oh, wow!
We'll go to market with
that crop, won't we?
Here you go.
I don't understand. How?
How do you think?
He fixed it.
Can you believe it, Nori?
There's enough bounty
here to feast tonight
and still have enough left
over to last to Frozen Fish.
Malva's sayin' she gonna make
somethin' called apple-sausage.
- Applesauce.
- That's what I said.
From Father.
Thank you, Malva.
Where's your sister gone?
We got it. Is there more
space in there? We're done.
♪ ...floated down it ♪
♪ So loudly she did wail ♪
♪ The King of the Frog Fishies ♪
♪ Turned her into a snail ♪
♪ Old Bolgerbuck he caught her ♪
♪ So juicy and so sweet ♪
♪ They say his little daughter ♪
♪ He could not help but... ♪
Wait!
You're going the wrong way.
He went that way.
Go on, now.
Nori!
- Leave her alone!
- You heard her.
- Off with you now!
- Begone!
You harm a hair on her foot,
and I'll brain the lot of ya.
Come on. All right. Keep your hands on.
Together now.
Whoa!
Give him to me.
No!
You're going home. Do you hear me?
You're coming with us.
Please. Berek.
- Please.
- He won't listen to you.
He won't listen to any of us.
I should never have
pulled the Elf on board.
I should've left her in
the sea, where I found her.
Theo?
The Queen Regent. Is she here?
Preparations are nearly complete.
We can depart within the hour.
What of the Southlanders?
One garrison will remain behind to
escort them to a safe settlement.
And search for our missing.
Galadriel.
No one kneels in Númenor.
You are not in Númenor.
Neither of you are.
A fault that is mine alone.
Our ships are waiting, my Queen.
Let us put this land behind our sails.
Do not spend your pity on me, Elf.
Save it for our enemies.
For they do not know
what they have begun.
For I, Míriel,
daughter of Ar-Inziladûn, vow this.
Númenor will return.
Then the Elves will be ready.
Captain, we sail with the tide.
Captain?
I got it.
On your feet now, girl. Stand
up. Help me gather what we can.
Nori, now.
Don't let this splinter your
spirit, it'll be all right.
Don't lie to her, Largo.
She's too old for that now.
I wasn't lyin'. It will be all right.
Pity's sake, Brandyfoot.
Give us a moment to weep.
Weepin'?
Is that all you think
we have left in us?
We're Harfoots!
Look, we don't slay dragons.
Not much for diggin' jewels.
But there's one thing
we can do, I warrant,
better than any creature
in all Middle-earth.
We stay true to each other.
No matter how the path
winds, or how steep it gets,
we face it,
with our hearts even
bigger than our feet.
And we just keep walkin'.
Nori. Where are you goin'?
To help my friend.
Warn him what's comin'.
He deserves at least that.
Goin' off-trail? Now? Alone?
She won't be alone.
We've left enough folk
behind, we're not leavin' him.
You girls aren't goin' anywhere.
Not without me.
You sure about this, Goldie?
You go into those woods, you
might never come out alive.
They might if a trail-finder
were to go with them.
Brandyfoot girl was right to
help him. Was right all along.
And if you think Malva Meadowgrass
is too proud to admit it,
well, what's the good of livin',
Sadoc, if we aren't livin' good?
You know, Malva, just once...
Once, it would be grand if
you weren't right all the time.
I'll fetch provisions and get me stick.
I'm comin' with ya.
It doesn't matter anyway,
we're all gonna die.
Come on, otherwise
we'll be here all day.
Think we'll be able to find him?
He's a bloody giant. How could we miss him?
You believe she'll keep her promise?
No.
I'm certain of it.
Bones have been set, wound
bound. We can travel.
Where will you go?
An old Númenórean colony
by the mouth of the Anduin.
Pelargir, they called it. They say
there's fresh land, fresh water.
A fresh start.
Then I will report to our High King.
To face whatever awaits me.
But what of our king?
Your king?
Has no one informed you?
Informed me of what?
Halbrand.
I thought you had died.
Better for me if I had done.
Southlanders found him on
the road like this yestereve.
The wound soured overnight.
I thought to try and treat
him on the road, but...
This wound needs Elvish medicine.
Can he ride?
I'll have the healers gather
what provisions they can.
Well, my friend.
It seems fate has in
store for us one more raft.
This is not over.
I will not abandon these
lands and condemn them to burn.
Nor will you.
Strength to the king!
Keep it... Soldier.
Commander.
Strength to the Southlands!
I failed him.
It's all my fault.
No.
No, it isn't.
Whose is it, then?
It's your father's.
He's grown too old, too suspicious.
His mind, too feeble.
His eyes too dim to see
that no matter how many
crests he hurls to the floor,
one day this will be your kingdom.
Durin IV's.
Not your brother's.
Not some other Dwarf-lord's. Yours.
And mine.
And together, we will rule this mountain
and all others before our time is done.
That mithril belongs to us.
To you and me.
And together, one day,
we are going to dig.
Seal it up.
My children.
Cast off your sun-cloaks and your helms.
You are no longer to
be burdened by the day.
This is our land now.
It is our home.
Hail Adar, Lord of the Southlands!
No...
That is the name of a
place that no longer exists.
What should we call it
instead, Lord-father?
Adar! Adar!
Adar!
- Synced and corrected by VitoSilans -
-- www.MY-SUBS.com --